A Guide to the Willis M. Carter Collection, ca. 1894-2016
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Willis M. Carter Collection, ca. 1894-2016
The Library of Virginia
51546
8.52 cu. ft. and 18 boxes
Willis M. Carter
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Deborah Harding of New York, New York; Cuesta Benberry of St. Louis, Missouri; and Jennifer Vickers of Staunton, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Willis McGlascoe Carter was born in Albemarle County, Virginia, to Samuel Carter adn Rhoda Brown Carter. Born into slavery the first of eleven children, Carter was educated at Wayland Seminary in Washington, D.C., became a teacher, a newspaper editor, and a statesman and political activist respected for his work to promote African American political rights and educational opportunities. He married Serena Bell Johnson (ca. 1869-5 August 1898) on 13 September 1888 and had two sons, Roscoe Wilson Carter (4 July 1889-28 December 1974) and Storum W. Carter (21 February 1893-28 February 1894). Carter is believed to be buried at Fairview Cemetery in Staunton, Virginia.
Cuesta Aldine Ray Benberry was born in Cincinnati, Ohio, in 1923 to Walter Ray, Sr., and Marie Jones, and was raised and lived in St. Louis, Missouri. Benberry was an esteemed historian, particularly of African American quilts and culture, a teacher, and a librarian. She married George L. Benberry in 1951 and had one son, George, Jr., born in 1953. Benberry died 23 August 2007.
Scope and Content
Collection, ca. 1894-2016, of Willis McGlasgoe Carter (1852-1902), an African American newspaper editor in Staunton, Virginia, consisting of a journal, ca. 1894, by Carter; issue, 1 September 1894, of Carter's newspaper, the Staunton Tribune; and a memorial, 1902, written by Carter's fellow teachers at Public School no. 2 in Staunton at Carter's death. Collection also contains additional research notes and materials gathered by Deborah Harding, Cuesta Benberry, and Margaret Rhett, including articles, interviews, maps, photographs, and court and federal records for the book From Slave to Statesman, The Life of Educator, Editor, and Civil Rights Activist Willis M. Carter of Virginia by Robert Heinrich and Deborah Harding, forward by Henry Louis Gates, Jr., published by LSU Press in May 2016. Collection also contains papers of Cuesta Benberry (1923-2007) of St. Louis, Missouri, who discovered the Carter journal.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Other Finding Aid
Consult both the on-line finding aid and the hard copy finding aid located in the first folder in the first box of the collection.
Contents List
- Collection contents list folder. (Box 1)
- Willis M. Carter journal. (Box 1, Folder A)
- Willis M. Carter memorial tribute. (Box 1, Folder B)
- Staunton Tribune (see box 18, folder 100). (Box 1, Folder C)
- Herringshaw's listing of Willis M. Carter. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Goodloes/Winns (3 folders). (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Ethiopian--Portuguese slave trade. (Box 1, Folder 2A)
- Goodloes-Lipscomb. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lipscomb. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Goodloes. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Goodloes/Fance Hill/Sneeds-Hemings. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Locust Dale--Sam Towler (2 folders). (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Jane Lew--Goodloes--Stephens and Jacksons. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- George A. Farrow--Brooksville (3 folders). (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Civil War--miscellaneous. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Civil War book--On the Home Front: A Civil War Diary from Augusta County, Virginia. (Box 3, Folder 10A)
- Southern Claims depositions (2 folders). (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Sawmill, 1868. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Hanger's Farm. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Chesapeake & Ohio Railroad and N. B. Shepherd/Hinton. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Capon Springs. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Porcelain Works and Waynesboro school. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Wshington--schools-churches-Baptists. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Newport, Rhode Island, and the Centennial. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Washington--Private Schools--Virginia Avenue--Drama Club Association. (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Washington--Columbian law building. (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Washington--city directories and 1880 census page. (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Daniel O'Brien. (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Washington libraries. (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Wayland Seminary. (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Wayland catalogues. (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Thom Brown Prize at Wayland Seminary. (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Cresson Springs. (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Rhoda (Brown) Carter Spears (mother of Willis Carter). (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Rhoda (Brown) Carter Spears (mother of Willis Carter). (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Rhoda (Brown) Carter Spears (mother of Willis Carter). (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Dorcas Carter Thompson. (Box 6, Folder 30A)
- Clara Yarber Brown Pickle. (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Augusta County schools--history. (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Supt. Charles Grattan. (Box 7, Folder 33)
- Smoky Row School. (Box 7, Folder 34)
- West End/Westwood School. (Box 7, Folder 35)
- Colored Teachers' Census. (Box 7, Folder 36)
- The Normal School/Peabody Institute. (Box 7, Folder 37)
- Augusta County Teachers' Association. (Box 7, Folder 38)
- National Memorial Association. (Box 7, Folder 39)
- Augusta County teaching career and pay records (3 folders). (Box 7, Folder 40)
- P.S. No. 2--Staunton. (Box 8, Folder 41)
- Staunton School Board minutes. (Box 8, Folder 42)
- Valley Training School. (Box 8, Folder 43)
- Francisco Newman. (Box 8, Folder 44)
- Willis M. Carter's marriage to Serena Bell Johnson. (Box 8, Folder 45)
- Serena Bell Johnson Carter. (Box 8, Folder 46)
- Willis and Serena Carter--the Davenports. (Box 9, Folder 47)
- Serena Carter--true reformers. (Box 9, Folder 48)
- Aunt Harriet Carter. (Box 9, Folder 49A)
- 414 North Augusta Street--Lee A. and William H. Carter--Kate, Luella, and Lillian Staples. (Box 9, Folder 49B)
- George Carter. (Box 9, Folder 49C)
- David C. Carter. (Box 9, Folder 50)
- I Garland Penn book--1891, first edition--The Afro-American Press and Its Editors. (Box 9, Folder 51)
- Handwriting comparison to Penn book. (Box 9, Folder 52)
- 1895 Atlanta Exposition. (Box 10, Folder 53)
- Danville Riot and Willis Carter on committee. (Box 10, Folder 54)
- Danville Riot--Frank T. Ware. (Box 10, Folder 55)
- Book--Jan Dailey's Before Jim Crow. (Box 10, Folder 56)
- Book--Charles E. Wynes' Race Relations in Virginia 1870-1902. (Box 10, Folder 57)
- Politics--Virginia history. (Box 10, Folder 58)
- Emancipation Day celebration. (Box 10, Folder 59)
- 1893 Roanoke. (Box 10, Folder 60)
- Campaign clubs. (Box 10, Folder 61)
- Willis Carter--Owensville (a different person also named Willis Carter). (Box 10, Folder 62)
- Republican convention and 1896 St. Louis National Republican Convention. (Box 10, Folder 63)
- Negro Protective Association--Richmond 1897. (Box 10, Folder 64)